<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//MAKUMBA//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "document-v20-mak.dtd"><document>
    <header>
        <title>mak:logout tag documentation</title>
    </header>
    <body>
        <section id="description">
            <title>Description</title>
            <p>To cancel out a certain attribute, in order to produce a new login, the logout tag is available
You can remove (cancel-out, logout) multiple attributes from the session by using &lt;mak:logout actor="attribute name"&gt; several times and/or by using the star (*) wildcard, e.g.:
(Later on, logout request might be done in the business logic, with a method deleteAttributes(param) that can accept either a String (with optional '*') or a String[]. ) 
(Later: to accomodate servers that don't do session tracking, login can be done by a query condition rather than by doing a query (once per session) to find an attribute. This way, it won't need to do a query (to check the authentication) at every access, but that condition will make sure that authentication is done. )

(&lt;mak:object from="best.Student stud" where ="stud.$login()"&gt; ...&lt;/mak:object&gt; 
then methodBestSudentLogin("stud") will return "stud.auth.email=$username AND stud.auth.password=$password" 
This can be used for http authentication with no session tracking. )
(Later: if an attribute has multiple values, a choose{AttributeName}.jsp page is shown. For example, a super user (for that area) can choose to act as any student, Lbg, or company... A student member of more local Vivaldi teams can choose to act for any of the viv teams, etc. )
</p>        </section>        <section id="attributes">            <title>Attributes</title>
            <table>
                <tr>
                    <th>Name</th>
                    <th>Required</th>
                    <th>rt expression value</th>
                    <th>Description</th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                    <td>actor</td>
                    <td>true</td>
                    <td>true</td>
                    <td>Document me please</td>
                </tr>
            </table>
        </section>
    
        <section id="seeAlso">
            <title>See also</title>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <a href="maklogin.html">mak:login</a>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <a href="mak attribute.html">mak: attribute</a>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
      <section id="example">
        <title>Example</title>
        <p/>
        <p>
    To cancel out a certain attribute, specify the exact name:
            <pre class="example">
      <![CDATA[
<mak:logout actor="student"/>
      ]]>
    </pre>
        </p>
        <p>
    You can remove (cancel-out, logout) multiple attributes from the session by using <![CDATA[<mak:logout actor="attribute name">]]> several times and/or by using the star (*) wildcard, e.g.:
            <pre class="example">
      <![CDATA[
<mak:logout actor="demo_*"/> (attributes whose names start with "demo_")
<mak:logout actor="*app"/> (attributes whose names end with "app")
<mak:logout actor="*"/> (all attributes; this "invalidates" the session)
      ]]>
    </pre>
        </p>
    </section>  </body>
</document>